<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Bugra Akyildiz</title><link href="http://bugra.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://bugra.github.io/feeds/30.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://bugra.github.io/</id><updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Unreasonable Effectiveness of Metadata</title><link href="http://bugra.github.io/work/notes/2014-01-30/unreasonable-effectiveness-of-metadata/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2014-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Bugra Akyildiz</name></author><id>tag:bugra.github.io,2014-01-30:work/notes/2014-01-30/unreasonable-effectiveness-of-metadata/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Metadata&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metadata could be translated as data about data if we want to translate
'mot à mot'. Generally, it defines what the data is about 
and gives some descriptive information around that. Still quite 
abstract huh? If the content of email is data, then sender,
receiver, date and time could be considered as metadata. 
Metadata could be quite important when data is not available or
unobservable due to various reasons. &lt;br /&gt;
One of the reasons why they could be collected quite freely and 
and abundant is because apparently it does not have to go through 
the same &lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/war_stories/2014/01/obama_s_nsa_reforms_the_president_s_proposals_for_metadata_and_the_fisa.html"&gt;privacy concerns&lt;/a&gt; unlike data goes.
Moreover, it is likely that its digital footprint is much smaller than
data and this leads to efficient storage, computation, analysis and
inference.
As its name suggests, it is an &lt;strong&gt;abstraction&lt;/strong&gt; of the data it sits on
top of the data; it does not necessarily tell the story, but that does not mean 
it does not reveal anything about data itself. Contrarily, it may expose a lot of 
interesting patterns and even not just about data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gmail Outage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week Gmail had an &lt;a href="http://googleblog.blogspot.in/2014/01/todays-outage-for-several-google.html"&gt;outage&lt;/a&gt; and users could not use their Gmail
accounts for almost one hour. &lt;br /&gt;
Consider this scenario, we cannot observe the outage of Gmail(after all 
it just prompts an error, temporary error 502), but we have all of the 
metadata of users who use Gmail. It would be quite easy to infer that
there is something wrong with Gmail infrastructure and this could be 
done pretty quickly and efficiently assuming we have all of the 
statistics and email metada information of users. Looking at the data of
the users has another important advantage; you actually do not care if
the infrastructure works but if &lt;strong&gt;your users&lt;/strong&gt; could actually use your
service. But is there a pattern to begin with? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Gmail Usage Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I used my work gmail account that I used from beginning of June 2013
up to January 2014. I looked at received email and sent email times. The
results was quite interesting. Although there are a lot of third party
applications which shows some usage statistics, I found none of them
secure and reliable. So, I pulled the data from Gmail using standard
library &lt;a href="https://nest.com/"&gt;imaplib&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from easiness, you could have control of all
of the folders in your email for arbitrary time intervals whereas third 
party applications generally either gives predefined(inbox, sent) or put restrictions in the time interval. Python has a batteries-included 
approach which works quite convenient at the times  when you want 
to do implement something that is already implemented in the standard
library. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Received Emails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emails Per Day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For daily counts of emails, Monday and Thursday has two days less than
other days this is due to the federal holidays.
But I must say most of the received emails are from project management
web app that we were using. When I looked at my received emails, I see
mostly notifications rather than "emails". 
&lt;img alt="Received Email By Day" src="/images/work/notes/2014/1/27/received_email_by_day_bar_plot.png" title="Received Email By Day" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do we infer from the above graph? For some reason, we have less
number of emails in Wednesday. Could it be we were working less in
Wednesday? Actually, yes. We used to have company meetings in Wednesday.
This may not change a lot for one person, but if you consider all of the
people in the company spent their times on the meeting, then total time
spent becomes 'meeting-hour * number-of-people' which apparently has an
effect on the total number of emails.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What!, you were receiving emails on Sunday?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we were a distributed team and Israeli team took vacations
on Friday and worked on Sunday. Those emails are mostly due to the
activities and emails from Israeli team. This would also lead to high
number of sent emails on Monday as you will see later. What I found
interesting is that, more or less most of the days have same number of
emails. Even though it &lt;strong&gt;feels&lt;/strong&gt; like beginning of the weeks are
stressful and hectic, apparently if we sum the number of emails per day,
we get similar number of emails for each day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emails Per Hour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following graph actually explains what type of email activity shows
a distributed and a team which has quite different timezones(USA,
Europe, Israel). 
&lt;img alt="Received Email By Day" src="/images/work/notes/2014/1/27/received_email_by_hour_histogram.png" title="Received Email By Hour" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emails Per Hour Over Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a "inactive" time zone which corresponds to between 3 am and 6 am EST.
However, as different people have are in different time zones, generally
the inbox email flow seems to be continuous except inactive time zone. 
&lt;img alt="Received Email By Day" src="/images/work/notes/2014/1/27/received_email_by_hour_month_scatter_plot.png" title="Received Email By Hour Scatter Plot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I have mentioned, the emails are mostly project updates,
notifications and lastly and in a small percentage emails. What is more
interesting is actually &lt;strong&gt;sent&lt;/strong&gt; folder as it will reveal my email and 
for some extent working behaviour. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sent Emails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emails Per Day&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, when I said the beginnings of the week was stressful and
hectic, it actually was. Generally, every week either task that I
was assigned in the previous week was completed or it the
method/algorithm/approach was not working, then we switch to other
approaches. Therefore, first two days of the week are mostly spent of 
trying to understand the task and try to figure out what is actually 
needed. This process brings a lot of questions and leads to high number 
of emails and communication. And, yes I was answering emails on Sunday 
time to time. 
&lt;img alt="Sent Email By Day" src="/images/work/notes/2014/1/27/sent_email_by_day_bar_plot.png" title="Sent Email By Day" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emails Per Hour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following graph actually explains a lot of my daily activity. Can
you see when I have lunch? Or when I commute to work or when I leave
from the work? Such daily behavior probably also affects my reactions and
responses to advertisements that I see on web. My probability of
responding to a restaurant or a meal ad around noon peaks whereas after
1 hour, I would lose all of my interest to food. Similarly, Uber ads
around 9 am and 6 pm would may mean a lot to me whereas I am quite
unlikely to respond to the ads at other times. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have two other accounts of in gmail which I use for my personal 
needs. With combination of those data, more or less my daily activity 
are actually could be inferred quite accurately from my gmail usage. And,
do not forget we did not yet go through my emails but only metada, 
timestamps of emails. Yet, even this much of data reveals a lot of my 
daily activity.
&lt;img alt="Sent Email By Day" src="/images/work/notes/2014/1/27/sent_email_by_hour_histogram.png" title="Sent Email By Hour" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Emails Per Hour Over Time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the following graph, could you see when I took vacation or switched to
another job so that my daily activity becomes almost zero? Could you
also see the activity in my transition and how it gets moved to
non-working hours (mostly).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sent Email By Day" src="/images/work/notes/2014/1/27/sent_email_by_hour_month_scatter_plot.png" title="Sent Email By Hour Scatter Plot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is more is of course whom I contacted, what tasks or projects that
I worked, what type of emails I received and sent. However, even without context,
even without using &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; data, I could go this far. With recent acquisition of 
&lt;a href="https://nest.com/"&gt;Nest&lt;/a&gt;, Google not only has our online activity(search, email) but 
also physical activities which it is fundamental to complete 
&lt;strong&gt;the cycle&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What is next?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is next is to infer the activities from data and predict 
what we will do next. In order to do that, Google needs abundant data
which it already has and machine learning algorithms that are effective
for unlabeled and large amounts of data, which it acqui-hires top-notch
researchers &lt;a href="http://www.cifar.ca/Google-DDNresearch-Geoffrey%20Hinton"&gt;Geoffrey Hinton&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.technologyreview.com/news/524026/is-google-cornering-the-market-on-deep-learning/"&gt;DeepMind&lt;/a&gt; in order to enable just that.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>